Finding Aid for E. Blythe Stason Papers 1929-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
E. Blythe Stason Papers 1929-1972
Stason, E. Blythe (Edwin Blythe), 1891-1972.
8676 Aa/2
University of Michigan law professor and dean of the law school, member of numerous governmental and professional organizations; organizational and subject files.
22 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received in different accessions between 1970 and 1972. The collection came from two sources: from the Law School of the University of Michigan, donor no. 343 and from the family of E. Blythe Stason, donor no. 5269
The collection is open for research.
E. Blythe Stason, dean of the Law School of the University of Michigan from 1939 to 1960, was a distinguished legal educator who also served on numerous state and national professional organizations and committees.
Born in Sioux City, Iowa in 1891, Stason graduated from the University of Wisconsin (A.B. 1913), from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (B.S. 1916), and from the University of Michigan Law School (J.D. 1922). With practical experience in both engineering and the practice of law, Stason joined the U-M Law School faculty in 1924 where he remained until his retirement on September 5, 1960. Within the University, in addition to his tenure as dean, Stason also served as Provost from 1938 to 1944.
Outside of his University responsibilities, Stason was frequently called upon for service to various governmental agencies and professional groups. He was a member of the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws; the Michigan Constitution Revision Commission; the Michigan Tax Study Commission; the Michigan Anti-Subversive Study Committee; the Attorney General's Committee on Administrative Procedure; the Hoover Commission Task Force on Legal Services and Practices of the Executive Branch; and the Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development (Administrator beginning in 1955).
Following his retirement from the University, Stason accepted a position as administrator of the American Bar Foundation serving from 1960 to 1964. He then accepted a position at the Vanderbilt University Law School where he taught from 1964 to 1970. He died April 10, 1972.
Because of his numerous and varied career activities, the Stason papers consisted of a large number of different groupings of files. For ease of access, these files have been grouped together into broadly defined categories or series corresponding mainly to similar kinds of professional activities. These series are Organizations and Activities concerned with Atomic Energy, Various state and national activities and interests, and EBS Personal
The E. Blythe Stason collection documents the activities of this law school dean, foundation head, and member of numerous governmental and professional organizations. Although there are significant materials relating to his tenure as Dean of the U-M Law School, the researcher should note that the bulk of those files will be located within the record group for that university unit.
Subjects:
American Bar Association.; American Bar Foundation.; American Judicature Society.; Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development.; Law.; Lawyers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws.; Nuclear energy--Law and legislation.; Stason, E. Blythe (Edwin Blythe), 1891-1972.; United States. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1953-1955); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan--Law School--Faculty.
- Organizations and Activities concerned with atomic energy
  Files pertaining to Stason's long-held interest in peaceful uses of Atomic Energy and in the legal issues associated with atomic energy have been grouped together. Subseries within this series include: Fund for Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, Atomic Energy Research Center/Atomic Energy Research Project (U-M Law School), Atomic Energy Study Commission of Michigan, and Atomic Energy Research and Subject File.
  - Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development
    - Ten year history 1954-1964 (Box 1)
    - General 1955-1972, 8 folders (Box 1)
      (files for 1960-1961 never received)
    - Annual meeting 1958 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws and certificate of incorporation 1954-1959 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors; Executive Committee; Meetings of Members 1954-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
      (mainly minutes, dates overlap somewhat)
    - Board of Directors; Executive Committee; Advisory Council (mainly correspondence) 1955-1958, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Financial reports and statements 1962-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Foreign interests
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - European program (Box 2)
      - Belgium (Box 2)
      - France (Box 2)
      - Germany (Box 2)
      - Italy (Box 2)
      - Luxembourg (Box 2)
      - Switzerland (Box 2)
    - Foundation grants 1956 (Box 2)
    - International Atomic Energy Agency 1958 (Box 2)
    - Japanese Science Teachers Visit 1971 (Box 2)
    - Library 1955 (Box 2)
    - Management and budget 1955-1957, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Management and budget 1958-1959, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - News releases (Box 3)
    - Personnel suggestions for staff and missions 1956 (Box 3)
    - Program file 1955-1956, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Progress reports and other literature (Box 3)
    - Projects proposed, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Projects (rejected) (Box 3)
    - Projects file (arranged by no.) 1955-1961
      - #1. India Mission 1955 (Box 3)
      - #3. Mexico 1955-1959, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - #4. Nuclear Congress 1955 (Box 3)
      - #6. Egypt 1955-1957 (Box 3)
      - #8. Turkey 1955-1957 (Box 3)
      - #9. Yugoslavia 1955-1958 (Box 3)
      - #10. Carnegie Exhibit 1955-1960 (Box 3)
      - #11. Distribution of literature (Box 4)
      - #12. Training facilities survey (Box 4)
      - #13. Publications (Box 4)
      - #14. Economic studies (Box 4)
      - #15. Austria 1955-1958 (Box 4)
      - #16. South American Mission 1956-1957 (Box 4)
      - #17. Far Eastern Mission 1955-1957 (Box 4)
      - #18. Burma 1955-1956 (Box 4)
      - #21. Japan Program 1956-1965 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - Publicity and information (Box 4)
    - Ruebhausen, Oscar 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Shorthall (John) reports and correspondence 1962-1969 (Box 4)
    - Special reports to the director (Box 4)
    - Special project reports (Box 4)
  - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project
    - Correspondence, applications for grants 1948-1952, 2 folders; 4 volumes (Box 5)
    - Project #30 (Legal Problems of Atomic Energy)
      - Correspondence 1952-1959 (Box 5)
      - Proposals and project reports (Box 5)
      - Patent matters under the Atomic Energy Act (Box 5)
      - Background information (contents of binder) (Box 5)
  - Atomic Energy Research Center/Atomic Energy Research Project (U-M Law School) 1955-1960
    - General, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Federal-State relationship (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous and pending projects (Box 5)
  - Atomic Energy Study Commission of Michigan
    - Papers 1955-1958 (Box 5)
  - Atomic energy research and subject file
    - Atoms and the Law (EBS book) 1957-1960 (Box 6)
    - Atomic Energy Act 1946 (Box 6)
    - Atomic Energy Act 1954 (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Atomic energy and research (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Atomic reactors (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Cisler, Walker (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Health and safety (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Insurance problems of nuclear enterprise (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-International Atomic Energy Agency (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-International (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-legal problems (articles and papers) (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy legislation and research, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy legislation-Germany (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy legislation-Michigan, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Liability for radiation injuries, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Patents (Box 6)
    - Atomic energy-Radiation accidents (Box 6)
    - Atomic Industrial Forum (Box 6)
- Various state and national professional activities
  The series - Various State And National Professional Activities - include subseries of material for the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws, the American Bar Association, the State Bar of Michigan, miscellaneous Michigan Activities, miscellaneous Federal Government Activities, and the Hoover Commission Task Force on Legal Services and Procedures.
  - National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws
    - General (Box 7)
    - Correspondence 1933-1966, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Committee assignments (Box 7)
    - Model State Administrative Procedures Act 1943
      (EBS was chair of the Special Committee on Uniform Administrative Procedure Act)
      - Correspondence 1939-1944, 7 folders (Box 7)
      - Correspondence 1945-1960 (Box 8)
      - Drafts, etc. (Box 8)
      - Suggestions and criticisms 1940-1943 (Box 8)
      - Comments on bill 1946 (Box 8)
      - Letters sent out enclosing copies of proposed act and acknowledgments (Box 8)
    - Model State Administrative Procedures Act (Revised) 1961
      - Correspondence 1958-1962 (Box 8)
      - Early drafts (Box 8)
      - Final drafts (Box 8)
      - Effect on state legislatures (Box 8)
    - Unclaimed Property Act (1954) 1951-1963 (Box 8)
    - Liquidation of Insurance Companies Act (1939)
      - Correspondence and papers 1935-1938, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Correspondence and papers 1939-1940 (Box 9)
      - Final drafts (Box 9)
    - Anatomical Gift Act (1968)
      - Correspondence 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Alfred Sadler correspondence (Box 9)
      - Articles and background information (Box 9)
      - Clippings (Box 9)
      - Early drafts (Box 9)
      - Final drafts and press releases (Box 9)
      - EBS testimony before U.S. Senate Committee (Box 9)
      - Duke University Conference 1965 (Box 9)
      - United Health Foundation/National Transplant Information Center (Box 9)
    - Uniform Enforcement of Foreign Judgments Act (1948) (Box 9)
    - Model State Tax Court Act (1957) (Box 9)
    - Uniform Photographic Copies of Business and Public Records as Evidence Act (1949) (Box 9)
    - Model Small Estates Act (1951) (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous model state acts (Box 9)
  - American Bar Association
    - American Bar Association Committee on Administrative Agencies and Tribunals, Judicial Administration Section 1937-1945 (Box 10)
    - American Bar Association, Section of Administrative Law (regarding Administrative Court of the United States) 1951 (Box 10)
    - American Bar Association, Committee on Improvement of Administrative Procedures, Section of Administrative Law 1955-1962, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Atomic Energy 1953 (Box 10)
    - American Bar Association, Public Utility Law Section 1937 (Box 10)
    - American Bar Association, Committee on Local Taxation, Municipal Law Section 1934-1937, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - American Bar Association (miscellaneous) (Box 10)
  - State Bar of Michigan
    - Board of Commissioners 1947-1950 (Box 10)
    - Committee on Administrative Agencies 1946-1955 (Box 10)
    - Committee on Judicial Selection and Tenure 1953-1954 (Box 10)
    - Committee on Disbarment of Subversives 1951-1955 (Box 10)
    - Committee on Constitutional Revision 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Michigan activities
    - Constitutional Amendments 1933-1936 (Box 11)
    - Financing education in Michigan 1933 (Box 11)
    - Legislative Committee on Administrative Rules 1947-1953 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Administrative Procedures Act 1951-1953 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Board of Commissioners for the Promotion of Uniformity of Legislation 1941-1954, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Michigan Constitutional Revision Study Committee 1942 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Intangibles Tax, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Michigan Sales Tax Act 1933 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Study Commission on Tax Administration 1957-1959, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Michigan Tax Allocation Act 1933 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Tax Study Advisory Committee 1944-1945, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Federal Government Activities
    - Agriculture Dept. administrative procedures study 1959 (Box 12)
    - Atomic Energy Commission (consultant services) 1960-1961 (Box 12)
    - Attorney General's Committee on Administrative Procedure 1939-1941 (Box 12)
    - President's Conference on Administrative Procedure 1953-1955 (Box 12)
  - Hoover Commission: Task Force on Legal Services and Procedures
    - Correspondence and other papers 1953-1958, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Working papers 1954-1955, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Harris analysis of legal services and procedures report (Box 13)
    - Statements by organizations on practice before executive department 1954 (Box 13)
    - Draft final report September 1954, 10 volumes (Box 14)
    - Draft final report September 1954, 6 volumes (Box 15)
    - Draft bill and explanation (Box 15)
    - Draft bills and documentary (Box 15)
- EBS Personal
  - Topical File
    The subseries within the Personal series include a Topical File of miscellaneous subjects, Conferences attended, Articles and Speeches, and Correspondence (mainly from the period following his retirement from the Law School in 1960).
    - Administrative tribunals, exercise of discretionary powers (Thomas M. Cooley lectures) ca. 1950 (Box 16)
    - Administrative tribunals class 1954 (Box 16)
    - Air pollution paper 1966 (Box 16)
    - American Bar Foundation 1959-1969
      - Acceptance 1959 and resignation, 1964 (Box 16)
      - Administration and finances (Box 16)
      - Annual reports (Box 16)
      - Corporate financing (Box 16)
      - Correspondence 1960-1969, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Foreign Research Institute survey 1960 (Box 16)
      - Selected projects/research procedure (Box 16)
      - Stason addresses, reports, etc. (Box 16)
      - Ten year program (Box 16)
    - American Enterprise Institute 1965-1970 (Box 16)
    - Citizenship Clearinghouse 1956-1959 (Box 16)
    - Constitutional amendment (proposed) re duration of petitions 1959 (Box 16)
    - Cooper (Frank E.) memorial 1968 (Box 16)
    - Federal Trade Commission (B. Carroll Reece file) 1945-1946 (Box 17)
    - Griffin, Robert P. (Box 17)
    - Joseph P. Kennedy Foundation (Box 17)
    - Judicial selection (Box 17)
    - Missouri Plan (selection of judges), 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 17)
    - Motor Carrier Regulation research 1923 (Box 17)
    - Municipal Corporations Casebook 1935-1960 (Box 17)
    - State Administrative Procedure Legislation (Box 17)
      (address before the ABA, 1946)
    - Taxes and tax problems (Box 17)
    - Tax legislation memoranda 1952-1953 (Box 17)
    - University of Michigan faculty (subversion legislation, etc.) (Box 17)
    - University of Michigan Mental Health Institute (Raymond Waggoner) 1956 (Box 17)
    - University of Michigan miscellaneous (Box 17)
    - University Musical Society (Box 17)
    - Vanderbilt University Law School (Box 17)
  - Conferences
    - England 1949 (Box 17)
      (to study administrative procedures in Whitehall)
    - Atomic Industrial Forum 1953 (Box 17)
      (regarding atomic energy hearings)
    - European conferences 1954 (Box 17)
      (regarding legal aspects of private nuclear enterprise)
    - Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development (Mexico City) 1955 (Box 17)
    - International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy (Geneva) 1955 (Box 17)
    - Endicott House seminar 1955 (Box 18)
    - Inter-American Bar Association 1956 (Box 18)
    - Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development (Brussels) 1956, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - American Bar Association (London) 1957 (Box 18)
    - Arden House Conference on Atomic Energy 1957 (Box 18)
    - Conference on Issues facing State Universities (U. of Texas) 1958 (Box 18)
    - International Bar Association (Cologne) 1958, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Soviet Union 1958, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development (Geneva) 1958 (Box 18)
    - International Bar Association (Salzburg) 1960, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Continuing Legal Education 1960 (Box 19)
    - Japan trip 1961 (Box 19)
    - UN Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy 1964 (Box 19)
  - Speeches and Articles
    - Bibliography of publications (Box 19)
    - Card file of speech notes and background (Box 19)
    - Dated file
      - 1922-1935 (Box 19)
      - 1936-1952 (Box 20)
      - 1953-1967 (Box 21)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence
    - Personal correspondence 1960-1972 (Box 22)
    - Personal correspondence 1959-1967 [A-Z] (Box 22)